Guide to the New York Radical Feminists Records, 1969-2011 RL.00948
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
New York Radical Feminists records
1969-2011
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
New York Radical Feminists
RL.00948
1.2 Linear Feet
The New York Radical Feminists (NYRF) was a radical feminist group founded by Shulamith Firestone and Anne Koedt in 1969. Collection contains organizing and theory documents as well as photographs from the New York Radical Feminists, as well as groups associated in some way with the NYRF or NYRF members dating from 1969-2011.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The New York Radical Feminists Records were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift from Lynne D. Shapiro in 2008, 2010, and 2011.
Historical Note
New York Radical Feminists (NYRF) was a radical feminist group founded by Shulamith Firestone and Anne Koedt in 1969 after they had left Redstockings and The Feminists, respectively. Firestone's and Koedt's desire to start this new group was aided by Vivian Gornick's 1969 Village Voice article, The Next Great Moment in History Is Theirs. The end of this essay announced the formation of the group and included a contact address and phone number, raising considerable national interest from prospective members.
Central to NYRF's philosophy was the idea that men consciously maintained power over women in order to strengthen their egos, but also held that women internalized their subordination by diminishing their egos. Shulamith Firestone and Anne Koedt left NYRF in 1970, but the group continued to be active through the mid-1970s. Its activities during that time included holding monthly consciousness raising meetings, publishing a regular newsletter, and maintaining a speaker's bureau. NYRF also organized a number of public conferences and speak-outs through the early to mid-1970s on topics such as rape, sexual abuse, prostitution, marriage, lesbianism, motherhood, illegitimacy, class, and work.
Collection Overview
The first 14 folders of the collection (acc. 2008-0262; dated 1969-1985) contain organizing and theory documents of the New York Radical Feminists, such as the first introduction to the group completed on December 5, 1969 by Shulamith Firestone and Anne Koedt with other members of its founding Stanton-Anthony Brigade (formed on October 3, 1969). Also included are consciousness raising topics and guidelines, lists of accomplishments and activities from 1971-1976, as well as notes from a 1971 session of the Lucy Stone Brigade; materials documenting speak-outs, conferences, and other activities; public relations and financial documents; and copies of the NYRF newsletter (1970-1977). Documents include originals as well as photocopies.
The collection includes a USB flash drive with images from the collection. These images are page scans of the entire collection except for the newsletters. Contents of the flash drive have been transferred to a library server.
Folder 15 in box 1 (acc. 2010-0203; dated 1972-1984) contains a selection of materials documenting enterprises that NYRF members participated in such as Mother Courage Restaurant, Womanbooks, Women’s CoffeeHouse, the New York Feminist Federal Credit Union, and the Women Like Me Oratory Group. Included are clippings, fliers, handouts, programs, press releases, conference schedules, newsletters, fund-raising letters, and photographs.
Box 2 of the collection (acc. 2011-0114; dated 1970-2011) contains material documenting NYRF member participation in other groups. Included are clippings, fliers, and other documents related to a range of events and spaces such as Women's Equality Day events, 35 West 22nd Street Women’s Center, East 5th Street Abandoned Women's Shelter Takeover, and the 1974-1975 New York City Feminist Community Coalition.
Feminists -- New York (State); Feminism -- History; Photographs; Newsletters; New York Radical Feminists; New York Radical Feminists; Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture
- New York Radical Feminists Records, 1969-2011
  - Introductions - Consciousness Raising Group Guidelines, 1969-1976 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - First draft - New York Legislative Program, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Lucy Stone Brigade notes, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Speak-outs, conferences, and other activities around the sexual abuse of women and children, 1971-1976 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Speak-outs, conferences, and other activities around marriage and motherhood, 1973-1975 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Production of "Focus on Me!" by Bobby Ausubel, 1974-1985 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Women and Work conference, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Retro-Fashion speak-out, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Newsletters, 1970-1977 (Box 1, Folder 9-14)
  - Selection of NYRF member activities, 1972-1984 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - NYRF member participation in other groups, 1972-1984 (Box 2, Folder 1-2)